Ever wished you could have
like a website or an
app designed, you know, like
in the blink of an
eye, perfectly tailored to your
exact needs?
Well, that's exactly what we're
diving into today, generative UI.
Yeah, it's not just about
making things look pretty, though
it can certainly do that.
It's about having, you know,
like an AI craft digital
interfaces that adapt to you,
you know, in real time.
No more wrestling with clunky
menus or trying to find
that one button hidden in
a sea of options.
This is about interfaces that
almost understand what you want
to achieve and they morph
to help you get there.
It's fascinating. You know, Harrison
Chase, the founder of LangChain,
he's been talking about how
user experience is this major
bottleneck in AI development.
He argues that if we
want AI to truly be
helpful, it needs to interact
with us in a way
that feels natural.
Intuitive.
Generative UI might just be
the key.
That makes total sense. It's
like we've been so focused
on on building the brains
of these AI systems that
we forgot about the face
they show to the world.
Exactly. And that's where generative
UI gets really interesting.
It's like having an AI
design assistant that can just
whip up a custom made
interface for any task on
the fly.
Like imagine telling your AI,
I need to book a
flight to Paris.
And instead of being, you
know, redirected to some generic
booking site, it creates a
streamlined interface right there in
front of you with only
the options relevant to your
request.
Now, that's what I'm talking
about. It sounds almost magical.
But how does it how
does it actually work?
Are we talking about AI
writing lines of code from
scratch?
In a way, yes. There
are different approaches to generative
UI. And one way to
think about it is is
on a spectrum of control.
On one end, you have
what we call true generative
UI, where the AI has,
you know, free reign to
generate the raw HTML, CSS
and JavaScript that that make
up a website or app.
So it's like it's like
unleashing an AI artist with
a license to design, you
know, however it pleases.
That sounds both exciting and
potentially terrifying.
Yeah. You hit the nail
on the head. While the
the potential for innovation is
huge.
You know, giving an AI
that much freedom can can
lead to unpredictable results.
Think flashing buttons, misaligned text,
the whole nine yards, at
least with the current limitations
of AI.
Right. It's like it's like
those AI image generators. You
might get a masterpiece or
you might get something that
looks like it belongs in
a modern art museum.
Yeah. Yeah. Intriguing, but not
always functional.
So what about the other
end of the spectrum? What
if what if you want
a bit more control over
the AI's creative output?
That's where guarded generative UI
comes into play.
Instead of giving the AI
complete freedom, we set some
boundaries, some design guardrails within
which it can operate.
Think of it like providing
the AI with with a
set of templates, style guides,
free approved components.
So it's still generating the
interface dynamically, but it's it's
playing within a defined sandbox,
ensuring a more a more
consistent and polished look and
feel.
Precisely. It may not have
the same element of surprise
as true generative UI.
OK.
But it offers a greater
degree of predictability and control,
which is essential for, you
know, many real world applications.
Right. It's a it's a
classic tradeoff freedom versus finesse.
But enough theory.
I'm itching to see how
this how this generative UI
magic plays out in the
real world.
What are some of the
tools and projects that are
that are pushing the boundaries
of what's possible?
One cool example is this,
this combination of React, a
popular JavaScript library for for
building user interfaces with open
AIs language model.
OK. Open AI, the the
folks behind ChatGPT. So we're
we're talking about combining the
power of AIs language processing
with the the flexibility of
a web development framework.
Exactly. Picture this. You're a
developer and you need to
create a simple contact form.
Instead of writing all the
code by hand, you just
type a prompt into your
code editor, like create a
form with fields for name,
email and a submit button.
And the and the AI
just conjures up the code
right there in your editor,
like magic.
Pretty much. Open AIs model,
it generates the JSX code,
which is then converted into,
you know, browser ready JavaScript
using a tool called Babel.
The really cool part is
that this code is then
executed dynamically using JavaScript's function
constructor, meaning the interface is
literally built on the fly.
Wow. That's seriously impressive. It's
it's not just about generating
static code. It's about that
code, you know, coming to
life and and responding to
user interactions in real time.
You've got it. And this
is just scratching the surface
of what's possible. Have you
heard of Vercel?
Vercel. They're the company behind
Next.js, a popular framework
for building React applications.
The name Vercel rings a
bell. They're they're really making
waves in the development world.
Right.
What what have they got
to do with generative UI?
Well, they've they've released this
tool called Vercel V0.
And and let me tell
you, it's it's causing quite
a stir.
With VL, you can describe
what you want your UI
to look like using natural
language, plain English.
Wait, hold on. You're you're
telling me I can just
tell this tool what I
want my website to look
like and it'll it'll spit
out the code for me.
You got it. And not
and not just any code.
It generates ready to use
React code that integrates seamlessly
with with popular libraries like
Tailwind CSS.
So I don't even need
to be like a coding
whiz to use this V0
thing.
Like I can just tell
it, make me a website
that looks like a tropical
island and and it'll just
handle it.
Well, well, maybe not quite
that detail, but you're you're
getting the idea.
The the real power of
V0 lies in its ability
to kind of translate your
intent into into functional code.
It's like having a conversation
with with a designer who
also happens to speak fluent
React.
That's incredible. But but it
makes you wonder what what
happens to the role of
the developer then if if
AI can, you know, generate
code from simple descriptions.
Are we all out of
a job?
Yeah, that's that's a question
a lot of people are
asking.
And it speaks to to
the evolving relationship between humans
and AI.
Well, it's true that tools
like V0 can, you know,
automate certain coding tasks.
The the role of the
developer is far from obsolete.
In fact, it's it's becoming
even more important.
How so?
Because because crafting effective prompts
for these AI tools is
an art in itself.
Yeah.
You need to be able
to clearly articulate your vision,
you know, understand the nuances
of design, anticipate potential pitfalls.
It's it's not just about
what you want.
It's it's how you communicate
it to the AI.
So it's less about replacing
developers and more about augmenting
their abilities, giving them the
power to do more faster
and with greater precision.
Exactly. And the really exciting
thing is that this is
still, you know, early days.
Vercel isn't the only player
in this field.
There's there's a whole ecosystem
of of open source projects
like like Open V0, Prompt
2E, V0, Copilot Next that
are that are pushing the
boundaries of what's possible with
generative UI.
It's like a whole new
frontier for creativity and innovation.
What else is out there?
What should we be keeping
our eye on?
One development that has me
particularly excited is is Anthropics
Claude Sonnet 3.5.
This this AI model is
is making waves with its
its unique artifacts feature.
Artifacts. That sounds intriguing.
What makes them so special?
Imagine this.
You're you're working with Claude
asking it to to design
like a website layout.
As it's generating the code,
it it doesn't just show
you a wall of text.
Instead, it creates these these
dynamic visual representations of what
it's what it's building.
And these artifacts appear alongside
your conversation.
So you so you can
actually see the design taking
shape in in real time
as you're interacting with the
AI.
Exactly. It's like having a
live feedback loop between your
ideas and the AI's interpretation
of them.
That's incredible. It sounds like
it could revolutionize the design
process, making it much more
collaborative and iterative.
Absolutely. And this brings us
to another crucial aspect of
generative UI.
The the tools that bridge
the gap between AI models
and the interfaces we use
every day for cell ones
again is is at the
forefront of this with their
with their for cell AI
SDK.
The Vercel AI SDK. Tell
me more. What makes it
so special?
Think of it as a
as a toolkit, a collection
of building blocks that developers
can use to to integrate
generative UI into into their
projects.
It's it's broken down into
three main components. The AI
SDK core, the AI SDK
UI and the AI SDK
RSC.
OK, let's let's unpack that.
What's the what's the what's
the AI SDK core all
about?
It's the it's the engine
room, if you will. It
provides the the fundamental functions
for for interacting with AI
models like like generating text,
streaming content, creating structured data.
So it handles all the
behind the scenes communication with
the AI, allowing developers to
focus on building the the
user facing element.
Exactly. And that's where the
AI SDK UI comes in.
It provides developers with with
prebuilt components and hooks for
creating those those seamless interactive
experiences that that we've been
talking about.
So instead of writing all
that code from scratch, developers
can leverage these prebuilt elements
to to quickly assemble chat
interfaces, autocomplete features and even
those those handy AI assistants.
Precisely. And then there's the
AI SDK RSC. This one
is a bit more technical,
but equally important.
Don't worry, I'm ready for
it. Hit me with the
technical details.
Well, RSC stands for for
React server components. Yeah. And
it's a it's a powerful
way to build web applications
that are that are both
fast and dynamic.
OK, I'm vaguely familiar with
React, but how does how
does RSC fit into this
whole generative UI picture?
In a nutshell, RSC allows
you to render UI components
on the server instead of
the the client's browser, sending
only the essential information over
the wire.
This this this results in
faster loading times and a
smoother user experience, which is
crucial for those those dynamic
AI powered interfaces we've been
discussing.
So it's like having the
AI and the server working
together behind the scenes to
to create a seamless responsive
experience for the user.
You got it. And the
and the in the AI
SDK RSC is specifically designed
to leverage the the power
of server components.
Yeah. Allowing you to dynamically
stream UI elements based on
the AI's responses.
That's incredible. It sounds like
a match made in heaven.
AI generating the ideas, RSC
handling the technical heavy lifting
and and the user enjoying
a smooth personalized experience.
It's a it's a powerful
combination and it highlights how
the the different pieces of
the generative UI puzzle are
starting to come together.
So we've gone from AI
generating lines of code to
like dynamically building entire user
interfaces in in real time,
all thanks to these powerful
tools like like the Vercel
AI SDK.
Where do we go from
here? What what does the
future hold for generative UI?
Oh, it's an exciting time
to be, you know, following
this space.
Imagine AI that doesn't just
follow instructions, but like it
understands context.
It anticipates needs, maybe even
surprises us with with its
creativity.
So less like following a
recipe and more like having
a true design partner, pushing
the boundaries of what's possible.
Exactly. And and as those
AI models evolve, so will
the the tools and frameworks
we use to kind of
harness their power.
Right. The Vercel AI SDK
is a great example, but
it's just the beginning.
We'll see even more specialized
tools emerge, giving giving developers
greater flexibility and control over
the entire generative UI process.
It's it's like handing incredibly
powerful tools to a new
generation of of digital architects
who knows what kind of
of incredible experiences they'll create.
It makes you wonder what
what will the world look
like when when anyone can
create a custom made digital
experience with just a few
words?
How how how will this
change the way we work,
learn and interact with each
other online?
Those are some big questions.
It feels like we're we're
on the cusp of a
of a major shift in
how we how we think
about and interact with technology.
Absolutely. And it's not just
about the technology itself. It's
it's about the possibilities it
unlocks.
Imagine a world where where
education is is personalized for
each student, where where health
care is more accessible and
tailored to your specific needs,
where where entertainment is a
truly immersive and interactive experience.
Generative UI could be could
be the key to unlocking
all of this and more.
It's it's mind blowing to
think about the the potential
impact this could have on
our lives.
It feels like we're we're
just scratching the surface of
what's possible.
We are. And that's what
makes this such an exciting
field to be a part
of.
Generative UI isn't just about
changing the way we design
interfaces.
It's about changing the way
we experience the world around
us.
I don't think I'll ever
look at my phone or
computer the same way again.
This has been an incredible
deep dive. I I feel
like I need to go
back and process all of
this.
This amazing information.
Yeah, it's been it's been
a pleasure exploring these these
ideas with you.
Until next time.